In this task about the concurrency and conflicts
in Petri nets, we are given two Petri nets.
For the first subtask, we are supposed to
give all sets consisting of at least two transitions,
and all of those transitions need to be concurrently
activated for the initial marking.
So we take a look at our Petri nets, figure
out the initial marking, which for the first
one would be (1,1,1), because we have three
places with one token each.
For N2, this would be (1,1,0,0), because
we have four places and one token in s1 and
one token in s2.
So if we just write these down.
We have (1,1,1) over here, and we have
(1,1,0,0) over here.
Then we take all sets of two transitions and
figure out which of those are concurrently
activated.
We are supposed to do that like demonstrated
in the lecture slides.
So that basically means we first figure out
the preconditions for every transition.
So for N1, t1 expects
one token in s1 and one token in s2.
So this is (1,1,0).
For t2, the precondition expects one token
in s1 and nothing else.
So this is (1,0,0).
t3 expects two tokens in s2 and nothing
else.
So this is (0,2,0).
And t4 expects one token in s3 and nothing
else.
So this is (0,0,1).
Now, we can either just have a look at which
can be concurrently activated and then demonstrated
like in the lecture slides, by taking the
direct sum of these preconditions.
Or we can just work it out brute force and
take all possible pairs here and then take
the direct sum.
If the direct sum of these two pairs is less
than or equal than the initial marking, then
that means they're concurrently activated.
So that's how you could figure it out if you
don't have the Petri net, given that all,
and just have the preconditions for example.
But in this case, this is a pretty simple
one.
We don't have to write all of these down.
Let's just work it out step by step here.
So we take t1 and t2, we take the direct sum.
This would result in (2,1,0).
In this case, there's a two over here and
that's more than in s1 in the initial marking.
So the t1 and t2 are not concurrently activated.
t1 and t3, this would result in a three in s2.
That's also bigger than the initial marking
here.
So t1 and t3 are out as well.
Well, we see that pretty much immediately,
t1 and t4 are (1,1,0) and (0,0,1).
So the direct sum of
the preconditions of t1 and t4
are (1,1,1), which is less than or equal
to the initial marking, which is also
(1,1,1).
So this is how we would need to write it down.
That shows that t1 and t4 are concurrently
active.
Because we need to give the sets consisting
of at least two transitions that are concurrently
active, we say
the set of t1 and t4 is concurrently active.
Now we take a look at all the other ones.
t1, we already dealt with all the other combinations.
So we can move on with t2.
t2 and t3 would result in a 2 in the second
place, which is higher than the initial marking.
t2 and t4 would result in (1,0,1), which is
less than the initial marking.
So those are concurrently active as well.
So we write those down as well and say the
precondition of t2 direct sum with the precondition
of t4 results in (1,0,1), which is less than
or equal the initial marking.
So the set of t2 and t4 is concurrently active
as well.
We also need to consider t3 and t4.
So just for completeness sake, t3 and t4 would
result in (0,2,1), and that's higher than
the initial marking.
So that's out as well.
So we are left with t1 and t4 concurrently
active, and t2 and t4 concurrently active.
We can move onto the second Petri net and
repeat the same process there basically.
So if we, first of all, make some space here,
remove all of these, and now repeat the same
process for the second Petri net.
We, once again, take all the preconditions
for the transitions.
So the precondition for t1, it expects one
token in s1.
So the precondition for t1 in N2 is just one
token in s1 and nothing else.
So it's (1,0,0,0), because we have four places
here.
The precondition for t2 expects one token
in s2 and nothing else.
So (0,1,0,0).
The precondition for t3 expects one token
in s3.
So (0,0,1,0).
The precondition for t4 is two tokens in s4.
So (0,0,0,2).
t5 expects one token in s1.
Once again, we just take all the two pairs
of transitions we just worked through here,
take the direct sum, and look at if the direct
sum is bigger than or equal to the initial marking.
For t1 and t2, this results in (1,1,0,0),
which is perfect.
That’s our initial marking.
So we can immediately write down that the
direct
sum of the precondition of t1 and t2 results
in (1,1,0,0), which is less than or equal
to our initial marking (1,1,0,0).
So the set of t1 and t2 are concurrently active.
Moving on.
We have t1 and t3, this results in (1,0,1,0),
and the one over here in the third place
is not present in the initial marking.
So that's out.
t1 and t4 results in a two over here, and
there are no markings in the fourth place.
So that's out as well.
t1 and t5 results in (2,0,0,0), which is
one higher than these tokens present in s1
initial marking.
So that's it for t1, it's just t1 and t2.
Next we look at t2 and t3.
This results in (0,1,1,0).
There's no marking in s3 in the initial marking.
So that's out.
The same for t4.
There's no markings in s4.
So that's out.
t2 and t4 is out as well.
But t2 and t5 result in (1,1,0,0), which
is exactly our initial marking.
So those are concurrent as well.
So it's again the direct sum of the precondition
for t2 and the precondition for t5 result
in (1,1,0,0), which is less than or equal
to our initial marking.
So the set of t2 and t5 are concurrently active.
That's it for t2.
So t3, there’s no markings at all in s3
in the initial markings.
So we can skip all of that because all direct
sums are still going to have a marking in
s3, and that's not possible with our initial
marking.
The same goes for t4 because there's some
tokens in s4 and none in our initial marking
there.
But we've already considered everything for
t5 by looking at the other ones first.
There's no T6 or something we can pair with
t5 that we haven't already looked at.
So we can skip t5 as well and we are left
with just these two concurrently active sets
of t1 and t2, and t2 and t5 for our Petri
net N2.
Since we do not need to prove that there are
no other concurrencies, this is it for the
first subtask.
With that, we can move on to subtask two,
B, which is to give all pairs of transitions
which are in conflict in the initial marking.
To figure out if they're in conflict, we first
need to determine once again by their preconditions,
whether the transition is even active in the
initial marking.
That's the case if the precondition is less
than or equal to the initial marking.
So for t1, we have the precondition of one
token in s1 and one token in s2.
So (1,1,0), and that is less than or equal
to M0.
So t1 is active in the initial marking.
The initial marking for the precondition for
t2 is also active because that's just one
token in s1 expected.
So it's (1,0,0).
So that's also less than or equal to our initial
marking, and therefore active.
t3 is not active because that expects two
tokens in s2.
So we are not going to write that down.
t4 is active because there's one token in
s3 expected, which is the initial marking.
So we can write that down as well as precondition
(0,0,1), and that is less than or equal to
the initial marking.
Now we can look back at our results from the
first subtask, which was that t1 and t4 are
concurrently active.
That means they can't also be in conflict.
So we take out that pair basically and ignore
the pair of t1 and t4.
So we take a look at t1 and t2 now.
To show that they're in conflict, we need
to, we've already shown that they're active,
and now we need to show that the direct sum
of these two are not less than or equal to
the initial marking.
So basically if we were doing this step by
step, just doing this brute force, basically
we would show for every pair that the pair
is active, so less than or equal to M0, but
the direct sum is not less than or equal to
M0.
That means that there is a conflict between
these two.
For t1 and t2, the direct sum of the preconditions
would be (2,1,0), which is not less than or
equal to our initial marking.
Therefore there is a conflict between t1 and
t2.
So t1 and t2 are in conflict in the initial
marking.
t2 and t4 are not in conflict because the
direct sum of those is just (1,0,1), and that's
also less than or equal to M0.
So these are not in conflict.
We've also shown this in the first subtask
because t2 and t4 are also concurrently active.
And if two transitions are concurrently active,
they can't also be in conflict.
So that rules them out for this.
So we only have t1 and t2 in conflict for
the first Petri net.
Now for Petri net N2, we would basically repeat
the same process.
We first figure out which ones are active.
Just looking at the Petri net, we can already
tell only t1, t2, and t5 are active, because
t2 expects a token in s2, t1 expects a token
in s1, and t5 also expects a token in s1,
there's no other token.
So t3 can't be active and t4 can't be active
either.
Then we already know from our first subtask
that t1 and t2 are concurrently active.
So t1 and t2 can't be in conflict.
t5 and t2 are concurrently active, so those
can't be in conflict as well.
So the only pair that's left is t1 and t5.
If we look at the precondition of t1, which
is just one token in s1 and nothing else,
that's less than or equal to M0.
So this is active.
This is just writing this down once again
to prove it, because that's what the task
is asking for.
The precondition for t5 is exactly the same,
also less than or equal to M0, and therefore
active.
But the direct sum
of the two preconditions is (2,0,0,0), which
is not less than or equal to M0.
Therefore, the pair t1 and t5 are in conflict
in the initial marking in M0.
There's nothing else to consider.
So this is it for the second Petri net, and
that's it for this task.